<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached at the funeral of Mr. Nathaniel Aske, late rector of Somerford-Magna in North-Wilts by John Clark.</title>
            <author>Clark, John, fl. 1676.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1676</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 35 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A33279</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C4477</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R11583</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13301553</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13301553</idno>
            <idno type="VID">98926</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A33279)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 98926)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 450:24)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached at the funeral of Mr. Nathaniel Aske, late rector of Somerford-Magna in North-Wilts by John Clark.</title>
                  <author>Clark, John, fl. 1676.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 27 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for George Swinnock ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1676.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Aske, Nathaniel, d. 1676?</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons --  England --  17th century</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:98926:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:98926:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preached at the Funeral of Mr. Nathaniel Aske, Late Rector of <hi>Somerford Magna</hi> in <hi>North-Wilts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>John Clark.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>2 Cor. 5.2.</hi>
               </bibl> For in this we groan earneſtly, deſiring to be cloathed upon with our houſe, which is from heaven.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>George Swinnock</hi> at the Crane in <hi>Cheap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſide,</hi> over againſt <hi>Merc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s-Chappel,</hi> 1676.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:98926:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:98926:2"/>
            <head>To his highly valued Friend M<hi rend="sup">rs.</hi> 
               <hi>Anna Aske,</hi> late Wife of the Reverend M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> 
               <hi>Nathaniel Aske,</hi> Rector of <hi>Somerford-Magna.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Dear Madam,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>YOur deceaſed Husband was pleaſed that I (amongst ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny others much more worthy then my ſelf) ſhould preach his <hi>Funeral Sermon,</hi> and now at your requeſt I have publiſhed it: Not that I am in the least ambitious of being in Print, but would rather decline it. Madam, I am very ſenſible of all your civil Favours, yet would much
<pb facs="tcp:98926:3"/>more willingly have taken another opportunity to expreſs my thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs then this; but ſince you were pleaſed to lay your Commands upon me, I readily ſubmit. I muſt confeſs both the matter and method to be plain, and not in the least worth your Acceptance; but I well remember the ſaying of one that otherwiſe could ſpeak in an elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent ſtile, (which was this) <hi>That it is better that Gramma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians ſhould reprehend us, then that the people ſhould not under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand us.</hi> This Sermon was prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched principally before a Country Auditory, although I muſt confeſs there were many of my Reverend Brethren there, but they were the feweſt in number; and I did en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour
<pb facs="tcp:98926:3"/>to ſuit my diſcourſe to the moſt, and not the leaſt of thoſe Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend perſons, who underſtood matters of this nature much better then my unworthy ſelf. Madam, I deſire not to exceed the bounds of an Epiſtle, ſo as to make the Porch greater then the Building, but in few words to conclude my ſelf,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your faithful Friend and Servant, J. Clark.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_parishoners">
            <pb facs="tcp:98926:4"/>
            <head>
               <hi>To the Pariſhioners of</hi> Somer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford-Magna <hi>in</hi> North-Wilts.</head>
            <p>THe uncharitableneſs and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faithfulneſs of Relations concerning this Sermon, have at laſt conſtrained my Publication of it; chooſing rather to ſuffer the ſevereſt Cenſure of a Juſt eye, then the unworthy diſtempers of unkind Tongues. This Sermon was Preach'd at the Funeral of your late deceaſed Paſtor; al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though I confeſs all was not then Preach'd that is now Publiſhed, yet I do aſſure you all is Publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed that was then Preached, and
<pb facs="tcp:98926:4"/>is very faithfully and fully rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in this Copy. The God of Peace teach us the things that make for truth and peace, and to lay aſide Slandering and Lying: For the firſt of theſe ſins, which too too many are guilty of in theſe our days, read that dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Curſe mentioned <hi>Deut.</hi> 27.24. <hi>Curſed be he that ſmiteth his neighbour ſecretly;</hi> this was one of the Curſes that was to be read by the Levites in the hearing of all <hi>Iſrael</hi> under the Law, and all the people were to ſay, <hi>Amen.</hi> Now for that other ſin of Lying, let me beg of you to take the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of the Apoſtle, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.25. <hi>Wherefore</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>putting away Lying, ſpeak every
<pb facs="tcp:98926:5"/>man truth with his neighbour.</hi> I have obſerved theſe two ſins too frequent amongſt ſome of you, eſpecially of your late deceaſed Paſtor, which makes me thus free with you.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>I am your well-wiſhing Friend and Neighbour,</hi> Jo. Clark.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:98926:5"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Philip. 1. verſ. 23.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>For I am in a ſtrait betwixt two, having a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to depart, and to be with Chriſt, which is far better.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Cannot ſay theſe words were the choice of our deceaſed Brother, but they were frequent in his mouth ſome few days before he dyed, which was the grand mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive of my choice of them. Great was the ſtrait that the bleſſed Apoſtle was in, he was divided betwixt two Affections, car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried to different Objects, and they were in a manner contrary each to other: The Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion was, Whether to live in the Fleſh, or in the Body, were profitable for St. <hi>Paul?</hi> And what to chooſe, Life or Death, he for the preſent knew not. Great was his love to the <hi>Philippians,</hi> greater was his love to <hi>Christ;</hi> one while he was drawn with a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:98926:6"/>to be with <hi>Christ,</hi> far remote from the <hi>Philippians,</hi> another while he was drawn with an earneſt deſire to abide with his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved Brethren here upon Earth, and to be for ſome time removed from <hi>Christ;</hi> the great neceſſity of his Brethren did move him to deſire the later; his great love to <hi>Christ</hi> did perſwade him to long for the former. Now betwixt theſe two different Affections (which were contrary each to other) the Apoſtle had a great Conflict: And ſuch was his perplexity, that he knew not which way to turn himſelf, he was at a ſtrait what to make choice of; he was (as I may ſo ſpeak) as Iron betwixt two Loadſtones, drawn this way firſt, and then that. We read of <hi>Jehoſhaphat</hi> and the people, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 20.12. that they were in a great ſtrait, for the Text ſaith, <hi>They knew not what to doe.</hi> And we read that King <hi>David</hi> was on a time in a great ſtrait, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 24.14. But now much different was the preſent perplexity of this our Apoſtle, and that of <hi>David: Davids</hi> was in regard of evils propoſed, this was for the enjoying of good. <hi>Davids</hi> great ſtrait was concerning an evil which could not be
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:98926:6"/>avoided, but the Apoſtles was free and vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntary. <hi>Davids</hi> perplexity ſomewhat con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned himſelf, the preventing of his own evil; but now the Apoſtles was for the good of others, which was joyned with his own hurt.</p>
            <p>Behold here, as in a tranſparent Glaſs, a heart truly Apoſtolical; wherein he made known at once both his great love to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> deſiring to be with him; and withall his great love to his Brethren, willing to abide with them for their profit.</p>
            <p>I ſhall confine my diſcourſe to the later part of the words: And therein conſider St. <hi>Pauls</hi> deſire in regard of himſelf; and from thence take notice, Firſt, of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire it ſelf, and that was, <hi>To depart,</hi> or <hi>dye.</hi> Secondly, a forcible Reaſon implyed of this his deſire, for then he ſhould <hi>be with Chriſt.</hi> Thirdly, his opinion or judgment of that Eſtate, To be with <hi>Chriſt</hi> is <hi>far bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> or <hi>best of all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here are ſeveral Obſervations or Doctri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Concluſions that are clearly deducible from theſe words which time will not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit me to proſecute. I ſhall therefore pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:98926:7"/>you but with one, wherein I ſhall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to compriſe the ſum and ſubſtance of my Diſcourſe at this time: And that is, from St. <hi>Pauls</hi> deſire it ſelf, wherein Note,</p>
            <p>Doct. <hi>That Believers have in them a wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling expectation and deſire of Death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The riſe of this Obſervation is clear e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough: For one ſpirit works in all Gods people, and brings forth like effects, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though not always in the ſame meaſure. That therefore which is true in St. <hi>Paul, (viz.)</hi> That the coming of death was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected and deſired by him, is in ſome de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, ſooner or later, verified in all that are the Lords. We may ſee a lively inſtance of this in old <hi>Simeon, Luke</hi> 2.29, 30 <hi>Lord, now letteſt thou thy ſervant depart in peace according to thy word, for mine eyes have ſeen thy ſalvation.</hi> St. <hi>Paul</hi> likewiſe avers the ſame of all true Believers, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.2. <hi>For in this we groan earneſtly, deſiring to be cloathed upon with our houſe, which is from heaven.</hi> And that they are rather willing to be abſent from the body, and to be preſent with the Lord, according to that of 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.8.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:98926:7"/>
            <p>Now there may be ſeveral Reaſons given for the ground of this Doctrine, that you may the better believe it. As,</p>
            <p>Firſt, Becauſe Believers know and are well aſſured, that <hi>the day of death is better then the day of a mans birth, Eccleſ.</hi> 7.1. When a man is born he comes into miſery, a world of miſery; what tongue is able to expreſs the internal and external troubles of this life? I could enumerate in divers caſes, both as to the one and other, but I paſs them over. Now death puts an end to all theſe miſeries to Gods people; and therefore no wonder that the Servants of God have in them ſuch a willing deſire after death.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Becauſe a faithful Soul when it departeth is immediately after death with <hi>Chriſt: I deſire to depart and to be with Chriſt.</hi> And thus ſaith the Apoſtle it is <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius,</hi> it is <hi>better;</hi> yea, it is <hi>Multo melius,</hi> it is <hi>much better;</hi> nay yet again, it is <hi>Multo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis melius,</hi> (we muſt bear with St. <hi>Pauls</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>congruity of ſpeech) it is <hi>much more better</hi> to be with him. And to the ſame purpoſe ſpeaks the ſame Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.19. <hi>If
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:98926:8"/>in this life only we have hope in Christ, we are of all men most miſerable.</hi> Believers, the Children of God, are moſt miſerable, that is, if in this life, in this world, only for the preſent we have hope and confidence in <hi>Christ,</hi> and the height of our confidence reach no further, then we, we poor Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, we the Faithful in the world, we of all men are moſt miſerable, yea, we are more miſerable then any other men.</p>
            <p>Thirdly. Again, Believers have in them a willing expectation and deſire after death, becauſe they have hope in their death; <hi>Prov.</hi> 14.32. <hi>The wicked is driven away in his wickedneſs; but the righteous hath hope in his death.</hi> It is by death Believers come to be partakers of the object of their hope. The time when the righteous hath hope is in his death. In the evil day, in time of greateſt diſconſolation; when Friends ſtand weeping and wringing their hands; when ſpeech, ſight, ſenſes, ſtrength fail; when riches will not profit a man; when Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians are of no value; when all creatures prove miſerable Comforters; and when all human helps fail, then, then is a Chriſtians
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:98926:8"/>Soul full of hope, and may comfortably uſe this motto, <hi>Spero meliora.</hi> Though I leave loving Friends, near and dear Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, many outward comforts and enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, yet I hope to enjoy and inhabit <hi>an houſe not made with hands, eternal in the heavens, whoſe builder is God.</hi> So that Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers upon this ground are willing to dye, becauſe they have hope in their death.</p>
            <p>Fourthly. Again, Believers have in them a willing deſire of death, becauſe here they look upon themſelves but as Pilgrims and Strangers: They are in this world, but not of this world; for Heaven is a Believers proper Country, and a Believers deſire is after this Heavenly Country, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.16. <hi>But now they deſire a better country, that is, an heavenly.</hi> A wicked mans Country is here below; here he lives, and here he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires to live. An Unbeliever is a Citizen of the world, <hi>Terrae filius,</hi> a Son of Earth, he is one that minds only Earthly things; his delights, his contentments, his portion, his happineſs are in this life; ſee <hi>Pſalm</hi> 17.14. and there you will find it ſo. But now a true Believer is a Citizen of Heaven, a Free-Denizen
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:98926:9"/>of that Country where <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> is at the right hand of God. Believers do diſclaim and diſown the World as none of theirs: The World accounts them as Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, and ſo they account themſelves. And as they diſclaim the World, ſo they lay claim to Heaven; <hi>We deſire,</hi> ſay the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.2. <hi>to be cloathed upon with our houſe which is from heaven:</hi> And indeed there is nothing that a Chriſtian hath that is worth the having, that he hath as a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, but it is in Heaven, (as is well noted by a Reverend Divine) Houſes,
<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Jer. Dike.</hi>
               </note> Lands, Poſſeſſions, Goods, Riches, Honours; theſe men have not as Chriſtians, but as men; theſe are common to Heathens with Chriſtians. But there be many excellent things that belong to Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians as Chriſtians; and all theſe things are above in Heaven: Our Father is in Heaven, <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.9. <hi>Our Father which art in heaven.</hi> Our Mother is in Heaven, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.26. <hi>But Jeruſalem which is above is free, which is the Mother of us all.</hi> Our elder Brother and Head is in Heaven, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.20. <hi>He raiſed Chriſt from the dead, and ſet him at his own
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:98926:9"/>right hand in the heavenly places.</hi> Our Inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance is in Heaven, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.4. <hi>To an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance incorruptible and undefiled, and that fadeth not away, reſerved in heaven for you.</hi> Our Manſion houſe is in Heaven, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.1. <hi>For we know that if our earthly houſe of this Tabernacle were diſſolved, we have a building of God, an houſe not made with hands, eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal in the heavens.</hi> Our Subſtance is in Heaven, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.34. <hi>Ye have in heaven a better and an enduring ſubſtance.</hi> Our Hope is in Heaven, <hi>Col.</hi> 1.5. <hi>For the hope that is laid up for you in heaven.</hi> Now if all theſe be in Heaven, where ſhould Believers be but in Heaven alſo, and have a willing de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of death to be with their Father, and with his Son <hi>Jeſus Chriſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fifthly, Laſtly, Believers have in them a willing deſire of death, becauſe it is better to be with God then with men; better to be in Heaven then on Earth; in a ſtate freed from ſorrow, ſin and temptation, than in a ſtate ſubject to them all: for as holy <hi>Job</hi> ſpeaketh, <hi>chap</hi> 14.1. <hi>A man that is born of a woman is of few days, and full of trouble;</hi> but a few days, and thoſe days full
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:98926:10"/>of trouble. But now <hi>bleſſed are the dead which dye in the Lord, for they reſt from their labours, and their works follow them:</hi> Here the people of God labour for reſt, I, but when they come to dye, they <hi>reſt from their labour, Rev.</hi> 14.13. Now they reſt from their labours in as much as all tears are wiped from their eyes: No more death nor ſorrow; no more aches, pains, Agues, Feavers, Conſumptions nor pain doth take hold of them; and therefore no wonder upon this ground alſo, that Believers have ſuch a willing deſire and expectation of death.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Objection.</hi> Here ſome may object, That we ſee in many good Chriſtians a fear of death, and a deſire of life: And I my ſelf, (may ſome poor doubting Chriſtian ſay) do find that I am apt to tremble at the thoughts of death. How ſhould not death then be rather a day of miſery to be trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled at, than a day of happineſs to be longed for?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi> To this I anſwer, That we are to diſtinguiſh concerning death: For death is conſiderable two ways, (which is a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:98926:10"/>diſtinction we give of death:) Firſt, as it is in its own nature; Secondly, as it is altered by <hi>Christ.</hi> In the firſt ſenſe it is true, That death is the very Suburbs and the Gates of Hell, and a day to be trembled at rather then longed for. But now in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond ſenſe, Death it ceaſes to be a plague, and becomes a bleſſing, in as much as it is even a door opening out of this world in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Heaven. Now Believers look not upon death ſimply, but upon death whoſe ſting and venom is plucked out by <hi>Jeſus Christ,</hi> and upon that account it is exceeding com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable <hi>Christ</hi>'s victory over death, may ſerve for the incomparable comfort of all true Believers. Yet further I anſwer, That there are two things conſiderable in every Chriſtian, Fleſh, and Spirit, Corruption and Grace, and the beſt of Gods Servants have many inward perplexities at ſome times, and doubtings of Gods love and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour: For it is a known truth which our Saviour delivers, <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.41. <hi>The ſpirit is willing, but the fleſh is weak:</hi> And as in all other good purpoſes there is a combare be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the Fleſh and the Spirit; ſo there is
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:98926:11"/>in this betwixt the fear of death, and the deſire of death; ſometimes the one pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vails, and ſometimes the other, but yet al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways at laſt the deſire of death doth get the victory. I muſt confeſs many times, that worldly reſpects do often prevail with the deareſt of Gods children; care of Wife and Children, and the like, but theſe are their infirmities; and as other infirmities dye in them by degrees, ſo theſe alſo at laſt are brought under: And the Servants of God being brought clearly to ſee the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs into which their death in <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſhall enter them, do here with St. <hi>Paul</hi> deſire to <hi>depart,</hi> that they may <hi>be with Chriſt,</hi> which is <hi>far better,</hi> or <hi>best of all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus have I endeavoured to make good the truth of this Doctrinal Propoſition, <hi>(viz.)</hi> That Believers have in them a wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling expectation and deſire of death, with the grounds and Reaſons thereof: There remains nothing but the uſefull Applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion unto our Souls.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</hi> And the firſt Uſe is by way of Information. Here we may be informed of the different ſtate and contrary condition
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:98926:11"/>of good and bad men, of Saints and Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, of ſuch as fear God, and of ſuch as fear him not, when they come to dye. A good man doth willingly reſign his Soul to God who gave it; but a bad man is ſo far from deſiring of death, that he cannot ſo much as think of death or Hell without a great deal of terrour and fear. The very thought of death to wicked men, is like the Hand-writing againſt <hi>Belſhazzar</hi> upon the wall, which was very terrible and ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing. But now with good men death makes way for their eternal happineſs. <hi>Though I walk in the vale of the ſhadow of death,</hi> ſaith holy <hi>David,</hi> Pſal. 23. <hi>yet will I fear none ill.</hi> St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> ſpeaking of the nature of death to Believers, ſaith, it is <hi>Janua vitae, Victoria belli, Portus maris,</hi> the Gate of Life, the Victory of War, the Haven of the Sea. Death to Gods people, is as the Angel was to St. <hi>Peter,</hi> to fetch him out of priſon, and ſet him at liberty, <hi>Acts</hi> 12.7. or as <hi>Pharaoh</hi> his Meſſenger was to <hi>Joſeph,</hi> to remove him out of the Dungeon into <hi>Pharaoh</hi>'s Court, <hi>Gen.</hi> 41.14. where he was highly advanced to honour and dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity.
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:98926:12"/>Believers are willing to dye, becauſe death puts an end to ſin; not only to the Dominion of ſin, but alſo to the very Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of ſin; ſin ſhall never moleſt them any more; when death comes they ſhall ſin no more, nor ſorrow no more, they ſhall go to that place where all tears ſhall be wiped away from their eyes, and live with God and Chriſt, with Angels and Juſt men made perfect for evermore.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</hi> The ſecond Uſe is by way of Reprehenſion. This may ſerve for a juſt reproof of them that are altogether unwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to dye: But come now and let us reaſon the caſe together; What perſon is there amongſt us, that if he were cloathed only with ragged and much worn cloaths, would not be willing to be uncloathed of them, and to be cloathed with better? And what elſe is this mortal and corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble body, but as ragged and rotten cloaths wherewith we are cloathed? Why then ſhould we not be willing to be ſhifted of theſe cloaths, of this mortal and corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble body, and to be cloathed with our houſe which is from Heaven, even with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corruption
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:98926:12"/>and immortality? Again, what perſon is there amongſt us, that if he were in Priſon, would not be willing to be ſet at liberty? or being in a place where he is but a Stranger, would not be willing to be at home? And what elſe is this ſinful Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, but as a priſon of the Soul, wherein the Soul is ſo ſhut up, that it hath ſmall liberty untill it return to God who gave it? Or what elſe indeed is this world, but as a place wherein we wander as Pilgrims and Strangers, and have no abiding City? Why ſhould we not then be willing to remove out of this priſon of the body, and to be received into the glorious liberty of the Sons of God? or to looſe Anchor from this Land wherein we are but Strangers, and by death to ſail towards Heaven, where our home and abiding City is? My Belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, it were well that Chriſtians would meditate much on Heavenly Glory: God hath revealed this Glory to the Elect, and their intereſt in it, that their thoughts might continually dwell upon it. It will be very profitable for Believers to muſe much on the happineſs of the other world:
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:98926:13"/>as, Firſt, it will abate our thirſt after Worldly Glory: Secondly, it will make Sufferings light: Thirdly, it will make us much more ſerious in Duties of Religion: Fourthly, it will make us, with St. <hi>Paul,</hi> more deſirous of death. Firſt, if Chriſtians did but much meditate on this Coeleſtial Glory, it would make them undervalue the tranſitory Glory of this World. How comes it to paſs that Earthly Glory is ſo much affected, but becauſe Heavenly Glory is ſo little regarded? It is the Apoſtles grave advice to Chriſtians, <hi>Col.</hi> 3.2. <hi>To ſet their affections on things above, not on things on the earth.</hi> One hours muſing on the Glory that is above, would cauſe the Soul to be as a weaned Child, to the Glory that is below. When a man hath ſeen the glory of a Kings Court, he contemns all that ever he ſaw in a Country Cottage. A Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian that hath this Heavenly Glory before his eyes, will quickly caſt the beſt of Earthly Glory behind his back. Secondly, if Chriſtians did but conſider much of this Heavenly Glory, it would enable them to bear with patience the greateſt Sufferings
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:98926:13"/>of this preſent life. <hi>I reckon</hi> (ſaith the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.18.) <hi>that the ſufferings of this preſent life are not worthy to be compared with the glory which ſhall be revealed in us.</hi> He that hath his thoughts much on the Crown of reward, will deſpiſe the igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine and ſhame of the Croſs. <hi>Moſes</hi> when he had by an eye of Faith looked a while on the recompence of reward, choſe affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction with the people of God, rather then the great preferment of <hi>Pharaoh</hi>'s Court. Reproach for <hi>Christ</hi> was preferred to the treaſures of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> becauſe he had a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to the recompence of reward. And <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelf, who is far greater then <hi>Moſes,</hi> for the joy that was ſet before him, endured the Croſs and deſpiſed the ſhame. <hi>Ille moeret ſi ſibi male ſit in ſeculo, cui non po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt bene eſſe post ſeculum.</hi> The ill being of this life is not greatly ſadning to that heart that knows it ſhall have a well being in the other life. The holy Martyrs did chear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully kiſs the Flames, becauſe they had their thoughts on that Glory which was far brighter then thoſe Flames. Thirdly, if Chriſtians did but muſe much on this Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:98926:14"/>Glory, it would make them more exact in all the Duties of Religion, as to the real performance of them: For that Chriſtian will be moſt abundant, and moſt ſerious in Duties, who hath his eye in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven while he is performing of them. No Saints will have ſo exact converſations on Earth, as thoſe that have their converſation moſt in Heaven. We know what the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles advice to Chriſtians tend to, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.58. That they would <hi>be ſtedfaſt and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>movable, always abounding in the work of the Lord, becauſe they know their labour is not in vain in the Lord.</hi> Some few ſerious thoughts of Heaven would ſhake off lazi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and work heart-enlargement in all the Services we do for God. Fourthly, if Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians did but much think of this Heavenly Glory, it would make them more deſirous to be in the poſſeſſion of it. He that by holy meditation lives much in Heaven, will be weary of living long on Earth. When the bleſſed Apoſtle St. <hi>Paul</hi> thought of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with <hi>Chriſt,</hi> he deſireth a preſent depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, as in the Text. And ſo, many of the Fathers, when they did meditate on their
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:98926:14"/>Heavenly Country, thought they had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued long enough in their Earthly Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try. So that from what hath been ſaid of this Heavenly Glory, and the great profit and advantage that comes to Believers by meditating thereon; and that death puts them into the poſſeſſion of that Glory, me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks many Chriſtians ſhould not be ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing to dye, as ſometimes they are.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</hi> The third Uſe is by way of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation, not to fear death. Too much fear of death, argues want of Faith. Why ſhould we be afraid of that which is a part of our portion? why ſhould Chriſtians be afraid of that which is their beſt Friend? When death was in Satans hand, it was our Enemy; but now it is in Chriſts hand, it is our Friend. I confeſs Nature will be Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſtill, and death is a diſſolution, and ſo the enemy of Nature, the <hi>last enemy,</hi> as the Apoſtle calls it, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.26. I but though it be an enemy, yet it is a Conquer'd ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my. Wherefore then ſhould we ſo much fear it? I ſhall offer two Conſiderations to keep us from the fear of death. Firſt, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider to be under the ſlaviſh fear of death,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:98926:15"/>is an uncomfortable eſtate; the Apoſtle calls it <hi>a bondage, Heb.</hi> 2.15. which ſhews the uncomfortableneſs of it. The Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>by the fear of death they were held in bondage all their life long.</hi> Secondly, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der your Covenant, intereſt and relation ſhall ſecure your hearts againſt the fear of death. They ſhould not fear to live, nor yet to dye, who have God to be their God, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. for the ſting of death is gone, it is taken out by the death of <hi>Chriſt.</hi> Death ſeparates ſoul and body, but it can never ſeparate Believers from the love of God. And this the Apoſtle aſſures us of, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.38, 39. <hi>For I am perſwaded, that neither death, nor life, nor Angels, nor prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipalities, nor powers, nor things preſent, nor things to come; Nor height, nor depth, nor any other creature, ſhall be able to ſeparate us from the love of God, which is in Chriſt Jeſus our Lord.</hi> My Beloved, the Covenant of Grace holds beyond death; it doth not bring Believers only into a preſent enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God, but it is to bring them into a full, perfect and everlaſting enjoyment of God in Glory for evermore. The Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:98926:15"/>of Grace yields Chriſtians the leaſt part of their good, of their portion, of their happineſs in this life: The greateſt and fulleſt portion of good promiſed unto Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers by God in the Covenant of Grace, lies in the arrears, in the referves, in the full poſſeſſion of the inheritance after death. And then why ſhould Chriſtians fear to dye, and go to take a full poſſeſſion? why ſhould Believers fear to dye, and to enter into the joy of their Maſter? why ſhould they fear to dye, and go home to receive all the deſires of their hearts, and all the eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal preparations of glorious bleſſedneſs for their Souls? I beſeech you therefore that you would well ponder theſe things againſt thoſe diſmal times wherein death may be repreſented unto us as an ugly and grim thing: It is ſo to Nature indeed; but to Faith death is become very amiable, (as I have formerly told you.) There is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in the world that doth us ſo much good as death; for it is the beſt Phyſician; It cures all diſeaſes of Soul and Body, and therefore why ſhould we ſo much fear it? Now therefore for ever bleſſed be God for
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:98926:16"/>
               <hi>Jeſus Christ,</hi> that hath made in him even death, the bittereſt thing of all, to be ſweet and pleaſant to us.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</hi> The fourth Uſe is by way of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, that we may (with St. <hi>Paul</hi>) be willing to dye. Firſt, let us labour to get an intereſt in <hi>Jeſus Christ;</hi> and when we have ſo done, let us value the <hi>Lord Jeſus Chriſt</hi> more then ever we have done, even becauſe he did ſhed his moſt precious bloud to redeem our Souls. Had it not been for <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> we had been under the power of Death and Hell to this very moment: <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſuffered death to deliver us from death; <hi>Chriſt</hi> bare wrath to deliver us from wrath. And let us diſpute what we will, we ſhall never find pardon of ſins, or peace with God, but by <hi>Chriſt:</hi> his name only is the Prince of Peace; <hi>Christ</hi> only is the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diator of Peace; <hi>Christ</hi> only reconciles God and Sinners: So that then we can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be happy either in life or death, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out an intereſt in <hi>Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> Secondly, if we would, with St. <hi>Paul,</hi> be willing to dye, then our great care muſt be to get our ſins pardoned; for if once our ſins are forgiven,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:98926:16"/>then nothing which befalls us in life or death ſhall ever be an evil or hurt. What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever ſtate the unpardoned ſinner is in, it is a curſed eſtate to him: his life is curſed, and his death is curſed. But now when ſins are forgiven, the ſting, the poiſon, the curſe is gone, and nothing is for evil to ſuch a perſon: if he lives, life ſhall be a bleſſing; and if he dies, death ſhall be a bleſſing. So that we can never have any true or real comfort when we come to dye, unleſs we are aſſured by the Spirit of God that our ſins are pardoned. Much more I might add; but ſo much for the words of the Text.</p>
            <p>I know you expect ſomething from me as to this providence which hath occaſioned this Funeral meeting. Funeral Sermons are not comforts to the dead, but helps to the living; it is for their ſakes that ſurvive, that God hath given theſe occaſions. The cauſe of our meeting at this time, is to perform our laſt office of love to our deceaſed Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the late Reverend Rector of this place.</p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:98926:17"/>
            <p>I could ſpeak largely of his Birth and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beral Education, and therein tell you he was deſcended of a very ancient Family in the North parts of <hi>England.</hi> His Coat of Arms (of which you have a view) doth ſufficiently demonſtrate the Antiquity of his Family; but this being the proper office of an Herald, I forbear to ſpeak further to that. His life of late years, eſpecially ſince he came to this place, hath been attended with much trouble: Not that he hath been the cauſe of it, (as ſome of his profeſſed Enemies would make the world believe) for my ſelf and ſeveral others have again and again heard him declare, He never in the courſe of his whole life was Plaintiff but in two Cauſes, and but one of them tryed: And to defend himſelf may well allow of a better conſtruction then altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Contentious. Now in what I ſpeak of him, as a man he had his human frailties; but as a Chriſtian, and one that knew ſo much as he did, I hope he did bewail them. And I pray, which of us all are without our faults? <hi>Who can ſay, I have made my heart clean, I am pure from my ſin?</hi> Pro. 20.9.
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:98926:17"/>I, indeed which of us all can ſay this? I know ſome there are that talk much of a State of perfection on this ſide the Grave, but alas experience tells us the contrary, and that all our perfection is to bewail our imperfections, that we cannot walk more cloſely with God. I am perſwaded thus far of him, (and without breach of Charity I ſpeak it) That had he met with a more obliging people, he might have proved a more uſefull Paſtor. God was pleaſed to exerciſe him with a long and languiſhing Sickneſs, which at length uſhered in his Death. I could not but take notice, that in the extremity of his Sickneſs, God was exceeding mercifull unto him, even to the laſt, in continuing his memory and ſenſes. I was with him ſeveral times in his Sickneſs, but more eſpecially the Wedneſday before he died, and then had ſome private confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence with him, in which I receiv'd much ſatisfaction from him. He then (and at other times) told me, he forgave all the World, and ſolemnly and ſeriouſly took the Sacrament of the Lords Supper upon it, He told me, he wholly relied upon the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:98926:18"/>merits of <hi>Chriſt</hi> for Salvation; adding with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, that he did really by Faith apprehend that infinite ſatisfaction in the bloud of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> as did fully anſwer all his fears, and reſolve all his doubts. He knew and was well aſſured, that the greateſt of Sinners might be ſaved by that bloud, and that the leaſt of Sinners could not be ſaved without it. He died in the Faith of the Church of <hi>England</hi> as it is now by Law eſtabliſhed, he owned the Doctrine and Diſcipline thereof, and withall wiſhed peace and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity to it.</p>
            <p>He was a carefull provider for his Wife and Children, and (conſidering his extreme Sickneſs at times) he had a tender regard of them, which he did fully manifeſt towards his dear Wife at his death, having that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidence in her, that he left the ſole manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his Eſtate to her prudent care. To conclude all, he had the charity to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give all, and we ought as Chriſtians to have the charity to forget all. In few words, to ſuch of you as were his profeſſed Enemies, let me beſpeak you of having a care of raſh judging of him, as to his future and final
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:98926:18"/>eſtate; for it was in the power of God to ſave him, and which of you all dare ſay it was not in his purpoſe. Now if any perſon ſhall charge me with flattery in what I have ſpoken of our dear Brother, I ſhall anſwer them in the words of St. <hi>Paul, Rom.</hi> 9.1. <hi>I ſay the truth in Christ, I lye not, my conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence alſo bearing me witneſs,</hi> that in what I have ſpoken of him is agreeable to Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Faith and Charity.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
